So, the answer is the first one. This is just
答案是第一个 它只有一个数字3
a number three. And we can get three from expression
我们可以根据这条规则得到数字 3
by following this rule. Starting from expression, replacing with number,
从表达式开始 用数字替换
and then replacing number with the number three. The second one
然后再用数字 3 替换数字
is not valid. And the way to see that is
第二个不是合法表达式
if we start from expression, we only have three choices. We
原因是从表达式出发 我们只有三种选择
can replace it with expression operator expression. We can replace
使用表达式 运算符 表达式替换
it with number, or we can replace it with a left
或使用数字替换
paren, expression, right paren. Since the expression we're trying
或使用左圆括号 表达式 右圆括号替换
to match starts with a left paren, the only
由于我们要匹配的表达式以左圆括号开始
way to get it left paren is to eventually
最终我们只能适用这条规则
have this rule that replaces expression with left paren. When
替换成带左圆括号的表达式
we use that rule, what we get is the
当我们适用这条规则时 得到的是一个后跟表达式的左圆括号
left paren followed by expression. Now we have expression here.
现在我们有了这个表达式
From here, we've matched the far left paren and
从这开始 我们匹配了最外层的左圆括号
the far right paren. What we have left is this.
和右圆括号 并剩下了这些内容
We can replace this expression with paren expression,
我们可以用带括号表达式替换这个表达式
and we have paren that's replacing this expression using
我们适用这条规则把这个表达式替换成带括号的
this rule. And then we still have the
这时 之前的第二个右圆括号
second right paren that we had before. This isn't
仍然存在
going to match here because we need two right
这与这里不符 因为需要两个右圆括号才能匹配
parens to match. And the essence of this rule
这条规则的含义是
is that every time we open a parenthesis we
我们使用的每一个左圆括号
have to eventually close it. So we can't product
最终都应使用对应的右圆括号进行闭合
expressions where the parenthesis aren't balanced. So this
所以无法生成括号使用未成对的表达式
is not a valid Python expression. We can
因此这不是一个合法 Python 表达式
produce the third one, this has many nested
我们能够生成第三个表达式 它具有很多嵌套的表达式
expressions. We have three perens that are open, but
这里有三个左圆括号
we have balanced and closed perens. And the
不过也有三个右圆括号与它们配对闭合
way we can derive this expression, we'll start
至于如何获得这个表达式
with one expression that's our starting point. We
我们从一个表达式开始 作为起点
use this rule to replace it paren expression, paren.
使用这个规则替换成圆括号 表达式 圆括号
Now, we have an expression that starts with a one,
现在 我们有了一个以数字 1 开始的表达式
so we want to replace this expression with expression operator
所以我们把这个表达式替换成表达式 运算符 表达式
expression. We still have the outer parens that we had
我们仍然保留之前的外层括号
before. Now, we're working on this part. We want to to
现在来处理这里
replace this expression with a number and then with the
我们把这个表达式替换成数字 然后替换成数字 1
number one. We're going to replace the Op, the following
接下来替换运算符
operator goes to times rule. That's going to be replaced
下面的运算符使用乘法规则
with times And now we've got to replace this expression.
使用 * 替换运算符 接下来要替换这个表达式了
We're trying to produce this whole thing, so we're going to replace
我们尝试生成全部这些 所以我们适用括号规则进行替换
this with, using the parentheses rule. And we can keep going,
继续
we're going to replace this expression
我们用表达式 运算符 表达式
with expression operator expression. Eventually get
替换这个表达式
the two times and then do that replacement with parens again,
最终得到了 2 * 然后再次适用括号规则进行替换
to get the three times four. And not going to fill in
得到 3 * 4 所有的步骤我就不写了
all the steps here because they won't fit on the screen.
因为屏幕放不下了
But I hope you get the basic idea that we can
但是我希望你们建立一个基本的概念
keep doing the replacements, making complex expressions like this one. So the
我们可以通过重复替换 构建像这个一样的复杂表达式
fourth possibility is not a valid expression. There's no way
第四个选项不是合法表达式
that we can get An operator in front with this
我们不可能通过这条规则得到一个运算符在最前面的表达式
rule. There actually are rules in Python that allow us
事实上 Python 中有
to have an expression go to operator expression. But we
可以生成运算符表达式的规则
have two expressions here. There's a three space three. If
但是这里有两个表达式 这里是 3 空格 3
it was just the number 33, this would actually be
如果只是数字 33 那么这实际上是合法的 Python 表达式
a valid Python expression. Not something that we can produce
但是这并不能通过这里的语法生成
with this grammar though. And the first one is valid It's
第五个表达式也是合法的
not sensible, or necessary, to have er, nested
像这样嵌套括号是不实用且不必要的
parentheses like this, but we could always keep using
但是我们始终可以适用这条规则
this rule, so we can derive that expression starting
所以我们可以适用最后这条带括号的规则
from expression using the last rule with the parens,
获得这个以表达式开始的表达式
and we're going to end up with paren,
然后以括号结束
expression, paren, close paren. We can use that rule
表达式 括号 反括号 我们可以重复适用这条规则
again, we're going to replace the middle expression with expression
把中间的表达式替换成表达式
paren expression. Replacing this expression with the last rule.
括号 表达式 适用最后一条规则替换这个表达式
That'll give us expression surrounded by parens, and we still have
这最终使我们的到一个被圆括号环绕的表达式
the two outer parens on each side. So we can have
我们始终保留着外侧的两层括号
as many necessary parens as we want. It's not necessary, it
所以我们想添加多少层括号都可以 不过这没有必要
doesn't make a lot of sense. We would never actually want
也毫无用处 我们永远不会这样写代码
to write code that way. But it's still a valid Python
但它仍然是合法的 Python 表达式
expression. So recursive grammar rules like these are very powerful. We
这样的递归语法规则十分强大
only need a few simple rules to describe a big language,
只需几条简单的规则就能描述一门复杂的语言
and the whole Python language that we're going to learn in
我们在本课程中学习的 Python 语言全部都能
this course can be described this way.
用这种方式描述
We're not going to describe the entire Python language
我们不会像这样描述全部 Python 语言
this way, but what I hope is that you have a good sense for how grammars
但是我希望你们已经理解了语法的工作原理
work, and you can see that, even as
你会发现
we introduce constructs somewhat more informally as we
尽管随着课程推进 我们会引入一些非正式的构造
go on, that they could be broken down
但是它们都可以分解成
into these kinds of formal or placement rules.
这些的正式且实际的规则